Finding Aid for the The Advocates
Special Collections Manuscripts and Rare Books
The Advocates
1969-1975
Special Collections Manuscripts and Rare Books
MSS.0020
.84 linear_feet
Biography/History
“The Advocates” was a public television network presentation of KCET, Los Angeles and WGBH, Boston made possible by grants from the Corporation for Public Broadcasting and the Ford Foundation. The purpose of the series was to stimulate public participation, and understanding, by focusing on realistic choices that must be made in the future, by having both sides of the question presented, and by demonstrating the interest which public officials have in both reasoned arguments and the views of their constituents. Having a one hour time slot, the program topics varied depending on current news and concerns of the public. The program ran from October 5, 1969 through May 23, 1974; then again bi-weekly from January 26, 1978 through September 9, 1979.
Scope and Contents
This one cubic foot (2 manuscript boxes) collection contains information, primarily from 1969 and 1970, regarding the creation of this television debate program, program schedules, discussion topics, transcripts from the first season of broadcast (both official and unofficial, except for May 17, 1970), photographs, and problems with the FCC. The collection is arranged by subject. The appendix lists the names of the advocates for each show, their guests, participants, decision makers, and moderators.
- Agreements
  - WGBH Education Foundation and Carl Byoir & Associates, 1969 (Box 1)
- Correspondence
  - 1969 (Box 1)
  - 1970 (Box 1)
- FCC Decision
  - May 26, 1970 (Box 1)
- Journal Article
  - Private Schools for the Public by Robert M. Krughoff, Education and Urban Society (Box 1)
- Locations for Remotes
  - 1969 (Box 1)
- Magazine Mockup
- Newspaper Clipping
  - May 2, 1975 (Box 1)
- Photographs
  - (3) black and white contact sheets (Box 1)
  - (1) 8x10 black and white (Box 1)
- Plan for TV Debate Series
  - Public Affairs Programming, February 10, 1969 (Box 1)
  - Original Plan, June 3, 1969 (Box 1)
  - Addendum, June 16, 1969 (Box 1)
  - Theory and Purpose of The Advocates, July 24, 1969 (Box 1)
- Poll Questions
  - 1969 (Box 1)
  - 1970 (Box 1)
- Press Releases
  - September 16, 1969 (Box 1)
- Priority Projects
  - 1969 (Box 1)
- Program Schedules
  - 1970 (Box 1)
- Research Meetings
  - 1969 (Box 1)
  - 1970 (Box 1)
- Taxation on Churches
  - 1969 (Box 1)
- Topic Types
  - n.d. (Box 1)
- Topics w/questions (possible air dates)
  - Federal Requirements for Welfare Programs, October 12, 1969 (Box 1)
  - Indians: Outline of Arguments, December 17, 1969 (Box 1)
  - Divorce Reform, January 18, 1970 (Box 1)
  - Should New York, January 26, 1970 (Box 1)
  - Population Control, February 5, 1970 (Box 1)
  - Bottles, Cans, Jars, etc., February 23, 1970 (Box 1)
  - Problems of the Aging and Their Care, February 24, 1970 (Box 1)
  - Move United Nations Headquarters to Africa, February 26, 1970 (Box 1)
  - Integration, March 10, 1970 (Box 1)
- Transcripts
  - “Should the sale of the internal combustion engine be banned in California by 1975?”, October 5, 1969 (Box 2)
  - “Should Congress require work from those on welfare?”, October 12, 1969 (Box 2)
  - “Should the Goodell bill, calling for the withdrawal of U.S. troops from Vietnam by December 1, 1970, be adopted?”, October 19, 1969 (Box 2)
  - “Should Congress provide funds to develop a U.S. supersonic transport?”, October 26, 1969 (Box 2)
  - “Should the States adopt legislation allowing any woman to terminate pregnancy at any time during the first three months?”, November 2, 1969 (Box 2)
  - “Should we prohibit law suits over auto accidents and have each driver buy insurance for his own injuries?”, November 9, 1969 (Box 2)
  - “Should the federal government issue no further leases for off-shore drilling?”, November 16, 1969 (Box 2)
  - “Should involuntary confinement on the grounds of mental illness be abolished?”, November 23, 1969 (Box 2)
  - “Should criminal penalties for the use of marijuana be abolished?”, November 30, 1969 (Box 2)
  - “Should the police be relieved of responsibility for social problems to concentrate on major crime?”, December 7, 1969 (Box 2)
  - “Should we require each ninth-grade student to take a course in Afro-American culture and history?”, December 14, 1969 (Box 2)
  - “Should we stop giving Christmas presents to restore the meaning of Christmas?”, December 21, 1969 (Box 2)
  - “Should drinking drivers get mandatory prison sentences or treatment of first offenses?”, December 28, 1969 (Box 2)
  - “Should we legalize gambling on pro football?”, January 4, 1970 (Box 2)
  - “Should we use half of the federal gasoline tax for mass transit?”, January 11, 1970 (Box 2)
  - “Should we allow anyone to obtain a divorce after a six-months separation?”, January 18, 1970 (Box 2)
  - “Should Indian reservations be continued indefinitely?”, January 25, 1970 (Box 2)
  - “Should the United States continue to reduce its aid to developing countries?”, February 1, 1970 (Box 2)
  - “Should Congress limit farm subsidy payments to no more than $20,000 per family farm?”, February 8, 1970 (Box 2)
  - “Should we lift our embargo on trade with Castro’s Cuba?, February 15, 1970 (Box 2)
  - “Should the U.S. Army instruct every soldier to ignore any military order to engage in conduct that he reasonably believes to contrary to international laws of war?”, February 22, 1970 (Box 2)
  - “Should the Congress appropriate further funds to maintain, improve or protect land-based missiles in the United States?”, March 1, 1970 (Box 2)
  - “Should the U.S. government make contraceptives available to every American including teenagers and to conduct an education campaign to limit population?”, March 8, 1970 (Box 2)
  - “Should the federal government subsidize the development of prepaid group practice medical care plans, and make Medicare-Medicaid payments contingent on membership in them wherever they exist?”, March 15, 1970 (Box 2)
  - “Should criminal trials be televised?”, March 22, 1970 (Box 2)
  - “Should the U.S. end restrictions on low-cost foreign oil?” (Part I), March 29, 1970 (Box 2)
  - “Should the U.S. end restrictions on low-cost foreign oil?” (Part II), April 5, 1970 (Box 2)
  - “Should your city or town try to integrate its public schools through redistricting and busing?” (Part I), April 12, 1970 (Box 2)
  - “Should your city or town try to integrate it public schools through redistricting and busing? (Part II), April 19, 1970 (Box 2)
  - “Should colleges adopt a fixed rule expelling any student who used obstruction, sit-ins or other illegal physical force as a mean of persuasion?”, April 26, 1970 (Box 2)
  - “Should we outlaw sidearms for all but police, licensed guards and proprietors of small businesses?”, May 3, 1970 (Box 2)
  - “Should Congress resolve that the President immediately withdraw all troops, aid and advisers from Cambodia and commit no further forces outside Vietnam?”, May 10, 1970 (Box 2)
  - “Should your city provide methadone to heroin addicts?”, May 24, 1970 (Box 2)
  - “Should automatic probation replace prison sentences for all those convicted of non-violent crimes of theft?”, May 31, 1970 (Box 2)
  - “Should shareholders insist that corporations have special directors to represent consumers and the environment?”, June 7, 1970 (Box 2)
  - “The Middle-East: Where do we go from here?” (Part I: The case against U.S. support for Israel), June 14, 1970 (Box 2)
  - “The Middle-East: Where do we go from here?” (Part II: The case for U.S. support for Israel), June 21, 1970 (Box 2)
  - “So that women may work and men may share in family tasks, should unions demand that everyone be given the option to work full or half-time?”, June 28, 1970 (Box 2)
- Appendix
  - Advocates
    - William Bailey, May 24, 1970
    - R. Lisle Baker, October 12, 1969
    - October 26, 1969
    - November 9, 1969
    - November 23, 1969
    - December 7, 1969
    - December 21, 1969
    - January 4, 1970
    - January 18, 1970
    - February 1, 1970
    - February 15, 1970
    - March 15, 1970
    - April 26, 1970
    - May 24, 1970
    - Robert Braucher, June 28, 1970
    - Richard M. Coleman, May 31, 1970
    - Alan Dershowitz, June 14, 1970
    - June 21, 1970
    - Roger Fisher, March 29, 1970
    - April 5, 1970
    - June 14, 1970
    - June 21, 1970
    - Max Greenberg, October 5, 1969
    - October 19, 1969
    - November 2, 1969
    - November 16, 1969
    - November 30, 1969
    - December 14, 1969
    - January 11, 1970
    - January 25, 1970
    - February 8, 1970
    - February 22, 1970
    - Judith Hope, March 8, 1970
    - William T. King, May 3, 1970
    - May 10, 1970
    - Howard Miller, October 5, 1969
    - October 19, 1969
    - November 2, 1969
    - November 16, 1969
    - November 30, 1969
    - December 14, 1969
    - December 28, 1969
    - January 11, 1970
    - January 25, 1970
    - February 8, 1970
    - February 22, 1970
    - March 8, 1970
    - March 22, 1970
    - April 12, 1970
    - April 19, 1970
    - May 3, 1970
    - May 10, 1970
    - May 31, 1970
    - June 7, 1970
    - June 28, 1970
    - Kevin O’Connell, March 22, 1970
    - Joseph Oteri, October 12, 1969
    - October 26, 1969
    - November 9, 1969
    - November 23, 1969
    - December 7, 1969
    - December 21, 1969
    - January 4, 1970
    - January 18, 1970
    - February 1, 1970
    - February 15, 1970
    - March 15, 1970
    - March 29, 1970
    - April 5, 1970
    - Evan Y. Semerjian, April 26, 1970
    - June 7, 1970
    - Max Singer, March 1, 1970
    - Jeremy J. Stone, March 1, 1970
    - Robert Taylor, April 12, 1970
    - April 19, 1970
    - L. C. Waddington, December 28, 1969
  - Decision Makers
    - Walter J. Hickel, November 16, 1969
    - Richard Stewart, November 9, 1969
    - David Vail, M.D., November 23, 1969
  - Guests
    - Sen. Birch Bayh, February 8, 1970
    - Sen. Birch Bayh, March 15, 1970 [filmed statement]
    - Joseph A. Bell, March 22, 1970
    - Joseph A. Bell, May 3, 1970 [filmed statement]
    - Rep. Johathan Bingham, October 12, 1969
    - Richard DeKort, January 18, 1970
    - Dr. Herman Goldberg, April 12, 1970
    - Dr. Herman Goldberg, April 19, 1970
    - Rep. James Heinze, December 28, 1969
    - Rep. Edward Koch, March 8, 1970
    - Rep. Edward Koch, March 29, 1970 [filmed statement]
    - Dr. Toby K. Kurzband, December 14, 1969
    - Rep. Paul McCloskey, March 15, 1970
    - Rep. Paul McCloskey, May 24, 1970 [filmed statement]
    - Marvin Mandel, January 4, 1970
    - Sen. Charles Mathias, March 29, 1970
    - Sen. Charles Mathias, April 5, 1970
    - Sen. George Mathias, October 19, 1969
    - Robert Montgomery, February 22, 1970
    - Sen George Murphy, November 30, 1969
    - Sen Frank E. Moss, October 26, 1969
    - Gov. Louis B. Nunn, April 26, 1970
    - Sen. Claiborne Pell, February 15, 1970
    - Ester Peterson, June 28, 1970
    - Ray K. Procunier, May 31, 1970
    - Rep. Tom Railsback, May 3, 1970
    - Sen. Jennings Randolph, January 4, 1970
    - Sen. Jennings Randolph, March 8, 1970 [filmed statement]
    - Hon. Elliot Richardson, February 1, 1970
    - U. S. Congressman Sam Steiger, January 25, 1970
    - Jesse Unruh, October 5, 1969
    - Daniel Walker, December 7, 1969
    - Rep. Charles Whalen, March 1, 1970
    - Rep. Charles Whalen, April 26, 1970 [filmed statement]
    - Mayor Kevin White, May 24, 1970
    - Mayor Kevin White, June 14, 1970 [filmed statement]
  - Special Guests
    - Ray Blunk
    - Howard Hughie, December 28, 1969
  - Participants
    - Mayor Joseph Alioto, January 11, 1970
    - Charles Anderson, May 31, 1970
    - Anonymous, “Alice Smith”, January 18, 1970
    - Anonymous, Two Women, November 2, 1969
    - Manual F. Ayau, February 1, 1970
    - Harold Bales, November 9, 1969
    - Richard Bartlett, January 11, 1970
    - Richard Baxter, February 22, 1970
    - Prof. William Baxter, October 26, 1969
    - Robert L. Bennett, January 25, 1970
    - Gerald A. Berlin, January 18, 1970
    - Alexander M. Bickel, April 12, 1970
    - Alexander M. Bickel, April 19, 1970
    - Mrs. Hilde Birnbaum, March 15, 1970
    - Harold Bishop, December 14, 1969
    - Peter Bixby, March 15, 1970
    - Harold Boslow, May 31, 1970
    - G. Holmes Braddock, April 12, 1970
    - G. Holmes Braddock, April 19, 1970
    - Thomas E. Brennan, March 22, 1970
    - Robert Brooks, February 1, 1970
    - Secor Browne, October 26, 1969
    - Pearl Buck, November 2, 1969
    - Robert Burch, March 29, 1970
    - Robert Burch, April 5, 1970
    - Prof. Dennis Cavanaugh, November 2, 1969
    - Paul Cherington, October 26, 1969
    - Ansley Coale, March 8, 1970
    - Rev. William Sloane Coffin, April 26, 1970
    - Mrs. Carl Cohan, March 8, 1970
    - Grant B. Cooper, March 22, 1970
    - Walter Cronkite, March 22, 1970
    - Charlotte DeArmond, November 2, 1969
    - Arnaud DeBorchegrave, June 21, 1970
    - Dr. Karl Deissler, May 24, 1970
    - Vine Deloria, Jr., January 25, 1970
    - Prof. Alan Dershowitz, November 23, 1969
    - Prof. Alan Dershowitz, April 26, 1970
    - Dr. James P. Dixon, April 26, 1970
    - Richard R. Dodge, January 25, 1970
    - Sen. Robert Dole, May 10, 1970
    - Michael Dukasis, November 9, 1969
    - Abba Eban, June 14, 1970
    - Abba Eban, June 21, 1970
    - Daniel Ellsberg, May 10, 1970
    - Rev. Richard Engeseth, January 4, 1970
    - Cynthia Epstein, June 28, 1970
    - Richard Fagen, February 15, 1970
    - Rep. Tom Foley, February 8, 1970
    - Jose Font, February 15, 1970
    - Percy Foreman, January 18, 1970
    - Joel Fort, M.D., November 30, 1969
    - Officer Jerry Fortney, December 7, 1969
    - Jack Francis, February 8, 1970
    - Rep Donald Fraser, March 1, 1970
    - Orville L. Freeman, February 8, 1970
    - Louis Fuller, October 5, 1969
    - Charles Gain, December 7, 1969
    - Dr. Abram Gardner, June 28, 1970
    - Martin Geisel, May 3, 1970
    - Tom Gerety, April 26, 1970
    - Robert Goldfeld, December 7, 1969
    - Joseph Goldstein, January 18, 1970
    - Sen. Barry Goldwater, October 19, 1969
    - Sen. Charles Goodell, October 19, 1969
    - Sen. Charles Goodell, May 10, 1970
    - Paul Goodman, December 14, 1969
    - Richard Goodwin, February 15, 1970
    - Stafford R. Grady, June 7, 197
    - Rev. Billy Graham, March 8, 1970
    - James Grant, February 1, 1970
    - Petey Greene, May 31, 1970
    - Prof. William Griffith, March 1, 1970
    - Dr. Elgin Groseclose, February 1, 1970
    - Dr. George Habash, June 14, 1970
    - Dr. George Habash, June 21, 1970
    - Gene Haislip, May 24, 1970
    - Najeeb Halaby, October 26, 1969
    - Sen. Clifford Hansen, March 29, 1970
    - Sen. Clifford Hansen, April 5, 1970
    - Dr. Garrett Hardin, November 2, 1969
    - Maj. Gen Y. Harkabi, June 14, 1970
    - Maj. Gen Y. Harkabi, June 21, 1970
    - Dr. Donald Harrington, March 15, 1970
    - Mr. Pleasant Harris, May 24, 1970
    - Dr. James Hester, April 26, 1970
    - Mr. & Mrs. Corbett Hull, October 12, 1969
    - Robert A. Hurwitch, February 15, 1970
    - King Hussein of Jordan, June 14, 1970
    - King Hussein of Jordan, June 21, 1970
    - Frederick Jackson, May 3, 1970
    - Dr. Jerome Jaffe, May 24, 1970
    - Richard W. Jencks, March 22, 1970
    - James Jones, December 14, 1969
    - Reese T. Jones, M.D., November 30, 1969
    - Francisco Jose, February 1, 1970
    - Alfred Kahn, March 29, 1970
    - Alfred Kahn, April 5, 1970
    - Nick Katz, February 8, 1970
    - Harold Kaufman, M.D., November 23, 1969
    - Prof. Robert Keeton, November 9, 1969
    - Sen. Edward M. Kennedy, March 29, 1970
    - Sen. Edward M. Kennedy, April 5, 1970
    - Rufus King, January 4, 1970
    - Lester Lave, October 26, 1969
    - Winnie Lawrence, October 12, 1969
    - Judge Keith Leenhoups, December 28, 1969
    - Henry Levin, April 12, 1970
    - Henry Levin, April 19, 1970
    - Mayor John V. Lindsay, January 11, 1970
    - Martin Lobel, March 29, 1970
    - Martin Lobel, April 5, 1970
    - Frederick Ludwig, May 3, 1970
    - Dr. William Lynch, January 18, 1970
    - Gordon MacDonald
    - Mr. & Mrs. Nicholas MacDonald, December 21, 1969
    - Sen Gale McGee, October 19, 1969
    - Sen. George McGovern, January 25, 1970
    - Howard McKissick, October 5, 1969
    - Marshall McLuhan, March 22, 1970
    - Lt. Joseph McNamara, December 7, 1969
    - John Mackey, January 4, 1970
    - Rudy Malaya, October 12, 1969
    - Don Marshall, October 12, 1969
    - Prof. William Martin, December 21, 1969
    - Mrs. Kay Masway, June 28, 1970
    - Margaret Mead, November 30, 1969
    - Walter J. Mead, March 29, 1970
    - Walter J. Mead, April 5, 1970
    - Golda Meir, Prime Minister Israel, June 14, 1970
    - Golda Meir, Prime Minister Israel, June 21, 1970
    - Carmelo Mesa-Lago, February 15, 1970
    - Dr. Richard Michaels, January 11, 1969
    - Hattie Midifer, October 12, 1969
    - Rep. Abner Mikva, May 3, 1970
    - Stephanie Mills, March 8, 1970
    - Ron Mix, January 4, 1970
    - Robin Morgan, June 28, 1970
    - Calvin Morris, December 21, 1969
    - Desmond Morris, January 18, 1970
    - Thomas Murton, May 31, 1970
    - Ralph Nader, June 7, 1970
    - Pres. Nassar of Egypt, June 14, 1970
    - Pres. Nassar of Egypt, June 21, 1970
    - David Nisson, May 31, 1970
    - Abu Omar, June 14, 1970
    - Abu Omar, June 21, 1970
    - Dr. Edmund Overstreet, November 2, 1969
    - George Pancio, December 21, 1969
    - Dr. A. W. Pearson, December 28, 1969
    - State Sen. Nicholas Petris, October 5, 1969
    - A. Craig Phillips, April 12, 1970
    - A. Craig Phillips, April 19, 1970
    - Gloria Powell, October 12, 1969
    - Mrs. Electra Price, April 12, 1970
    - Mrs. Electra Price, April 19, 1970
    - Phillip Quellet, November 30, 1969
    - Gen. Yitzhak Rabin, June 14, 1970
    - Gen. Yitzhak Rabin, June 21, 1970
    - William Raspberry, April 12, 1970
    - William Raspberry, April 19, 1970
    - William Rees-Davies, January 4, 1970
    - Ronald Ridenhour, February 22, 1970
    - Andy Robustelli, January 4, 1970
    - Dr. Victor Rosenblum, March 8, 1970
    - Jerome Rossow, October 12, 1969
    - Pete Rozelle, January 4, 1970
    - Prof. Dean Russell, February 1, 1970
    - Ralph Salerno, January 4, 1970
    - Norman Sanders, November 16, 1969
    - Dr. Thomas Schelling, March 1, 1970
    - Dr. John Schnittker, February 8, 1970
    - Gary Sellers, November 16, 1969
    - Prof. David Sergeant, November 9, 1969
    - Craig Spangenburg, November 9, 1969
    - Prof. Ernest Starkman, October 5, 1969
    - Major General Fred Stofft, February 22, 1970
    - Neil Sullivan, April 12, 1970
    - Neil Sullivan, April 19, 1970
    - William H. Sullivan, May 10, 1970
    - John Swearingen, March 29, 1970
    - John Swearingen, April 5, 1970
    - Thomas Szasz, November 23, 1969
    - Dr. Karl Taeuber, March 8, 1970
    - Jerry Tinker, February 22, 1970
    - Jose Toriente, February 15, 1970
    - Robert Townsend, June 7, 1970
    - Dr. Gus Turbeville, December 14, 1969
    - Dr. J. Thomas Ungerleider, November 30, 1969
    - Gabriel Valdes, February 15, 1970
    - Dr. Charles Wahl, March 22, 1970
    - Barbara Ward (Lady Jackson), February 1, 1970
    - Morrison Warren, December 14, 1969
    - Andrew Watson, M.D., November 23, 1969
    - Dr. Kenneth Watt, March 8, 1970
    - Leroy Wehrle, October 19, 1969
    - J. Fred Weston, June 7, 1970
    - Dr. Jerome B. Wiesner, March 1, 1970
    - Dr. Richard Wilbur, March 15, 1970
    - Harold N. Williams, June 7, 1970
    - Otis Young, December 14, 1969
    - Prof. Joseph Zasloff, October 19, 1969
    - Franklin Zimring, December 28, 1969
    - Richard Zylman, December 28, 1969
  - Moderators
    - Roger Fisher, January 4, 1970
    - January 18, 1970
    - February 1, 1970
    - February 15, 1970
    - June 28, 1970
    - Victor Palmieri, October 5, 1969
    - October 12, 1969
    - October 19, 1969
    - October 26, 1969
    - November 2, 1969
    - November 23, 1969
    - December 14, 1969
    - December 21, 1969
    - December 28, 1969
    - January 11, 1970
    - January 25, 1970
    - February 8, 1970
    - February 22, 1970
    - March 1, 1970
    - March 8, 1970
    - March 15, 1970
    - March 22, 1970
    - March 29, 1970
    - April 5, 1970
    - April 12, 1970
    - April 19, 1970
    - April 26, 1970
    - May 3, 1970
    - May 10, 1970
    - May 24, 1970
    - May 31, 1970
    - June 7, 1970
    - June 14, 1970
    - June 21, 1970